<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Snmp on Andrés Álvarez</title>
    <link>http://aalvarez.me/tags/snmp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Snmp on Andrés Álvarez</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://aalvarez.me/tags/snmp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding SNMP and Net-SNMP</title>
      <link>http://aalvarez.me/posts/understanding-snmp-and-net-snmp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://aalvarez.me/posts/understanding-snmp-and-net-snmp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://net-snmp.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;Net-SNMP&lt;/a&gt; is a suite of tools used to implement SNMP (Simple Network Management Protocol). SNMP is a widely used protocol for monitoring the health and welfare of network equipment (eg. routers), computer equipment and even devices like UPSs. Net-SNMP includes tools with capabilities such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An extensible agent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An SNMP library&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools to request or set information from SNMP agents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools to generate and handle SNMP traps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A version of the unix &amp;lsquo;netstat&amp;rsquo; command using SNMP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A graphical Perl/Tk/SNMP based mib browser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-snmp-works&#34;&gt;How SNMP Works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SNMP allows a management station to treat its network as a distributed database of health and configuration information. SNMP contains a small set of operations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GET: Retrieve data from a network node&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GETNEXT: Retrieve the next element from a network node&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SET: Send configuration or control commands to a network node&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TRAP: A network node can send a notification to the management station&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;INFORM: An acknowledged trap (network nodes can try and send it again if no acknowledgement is received)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://computernetworkingsimplified.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/snmparchitecture1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;SNMP Architecture&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zenoss Monitoring Template Data Points</title>
      <link>http://aalvarez.me/posts/zenoss-monitoring-template-data-points/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://aalvarez.me/posts/zenoss-monitoring-template-data-points/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Content from this post is mostly obtained from &lt;strong&gt;Zenoss Core Administration guide&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Zenoss Core &lt;strong&gt;monitoring templates&lt;/strong&gt;, data sources can return data for one or more performance metrics. Each metric retrieved by a data source is represented
by a &lt;strong&gt;data point&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating a data point, there are some important fields that we can define for our data point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name:&lt;/strong&gt; Displays the name you entered in the &lt;em&gt;Add a New DataPoint&lt;/em&gt; dialog.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RRD Type:&lt;/strong&gt; Specify the RRD data source type to use for storing data for this data point. (Zenoss Core uses RRDTool to store performance data.) Available options are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COUNTER:&lt;/strong&gt; Saves the rate of change of the value over a step period. This assumes that the value is always
increasing (the difference between the current and the previous value is greater than 0). Traffic counters on a
router are an ideal candidate for using COUNTER.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GAUGE:&lt;/strong&gt; Does not save the rate of change, but saves the actual value. There are no divisions or calculations.
To see memory consumption in a server, for example, you might want to select this value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DERIVE:&lt;/strong&gt; Same as COUNTER, but additionally allows negative values. If you want to see the rate of change
in free disk space on your server, for example, then you might want to select this value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ABSOLUTE:&lt;/strong&gt; Saves the rate of change, but assumes that the previous value is set to 0. The difference between
the current and the previous value is always equal to the current value. Thus, ABSOLUTE stores the current
value, divided by the step interval.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create Command:&lt;/strong&gt; Enter an RRD expression used to create the database for this data point. If you do not enter
a value, then the system uses a default applicable to most situations. For details about the &lt;kbd&gt;rrdcreate&lt;/kbd&gt; command, go &lt;a href=&#34;http://oss.oetiker.ch/rrdtool/doc/rrdcreate.en.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RRD Minimum:&lt;/strong&gt; Enter a value. Any value received that is less than this number is ignored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RRD Maximum:&lt;/strong&gt; Enter a value. Any value received that is greater than this number is ignored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-point-aliases&#34;&gt;Data Point Aliases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance reports pull information from various data points that represent a metric. The report itself knows which
data points it requires, and which modifications are needed, if any, to put the data in its proper units and format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The addition of a data point requires changing the report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://aalvarez.me/posts/zenoss-monitoring-template-data-points/cpu_report.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;CPU Utilization Report&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To allow for more flexibility in changes, some reports use &lt;em&gt;data point aliases&lt;/em&gt;. Data point aliases group data points so
they can be more easily used for reporting. In addition, if the data points return data in different units, then the plugin
can normalize that data into a common unit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>