<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bootstrap on Andrés Álvarez</title>
    <link>https://aalvarez.me/tags/bootstrap/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bootstrap on Andrés Álvarez</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://aalvarez.me/tags/bootstrap/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Objects and Ranges With Cases in Ruby</title>
      <link>https://aalvarez.me/posts/using-objects-and-ranges-with-cases-in-ruby/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aalvarez.me/posts/using-objects-and-ranges-with-cases-in-ruby/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ruby&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.techotopia.com/index.php/The_Ruby_case_Statement&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;case&lt;/code&gt; statement&lt;/a&gt; provides some nice functionality to be used with objects and ranges. I was recently developing a small application in Ruby on Rails using blood test data where I had to check if a certain test item (i.e. HDL Cholesterol) value belonged to a certain range. I did not want to use a bunch of &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; statements and I actually found a pretty neat way to implement using the Ruby &lt;code&gt;case&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my application I have a Rails model called &lt;code&gt;Entry&lt;/code&gt; which represents a blood test result with a lot of field data such as blood glucose level, blood pressure level, etc. etc. I want to display this data in the view using Bootstrap 3&amp;rsquo;s nice &lt;a href=&#34;http://getbootstrap.com/components/#progress&#34;&gt;progress bars&lt;/a&gt; and I want the progress bar&amp;rsquo;s contextual class to be changed and determined by the range in which this data point sits in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we take &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cholesterol&#34;&gt;total cholesterol&lt;/a&gt; as an example, a quick Google search indicates that an ideal value would be less than 200 mg/dL, a high value (not good) would be between 200-239 mg/dL, and a very high value (definitely not good) would be above 240 mg/dL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To implement this, I created a &lt;code&gt;Recommendations&lt;/code&gt; module under the &lt;code&gt;/models&lt;/code&gt; directory. All classes belonging to this module will have different ranges to represent what I explained above. This is what the model directory tree looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;app/models/
├── application_record.rb
├── concerns
├── entry.rb
├── recommendations
│   ├── blood_glucose.rb
│   ├── diastolic_pressure.rb
│   ├── hdl.rb
│   ├── ldl.rb
│   ├── systolic_pressure.rb
│   └── total_cholesterol.rb
└── user.rb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>